Guide to the Miriam Nyhan Oral History Collection AIA.036
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Miriam Nyhan Oral History Collection
2006-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Nyhan, Miriam
AIA.036
0.67 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
Miriam Nyhan is an Adjunct Assistant Professor of Irish Studies and Program Coordinator at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House. She received her BA and MPhil degrees from University College Cork (NUI) and her PhD from the European University Institute in Florence. Her research often focuses on oral history and Irish immigration patterns. This collection consists of 21 interviews conducted by Nyhan in 2006 as part of her PhD research. She interviewed Irish immigrants, many of whom emigrated in the 1950s and settled in New York, to perform comparative research of Irish migration patterns. The interviewees in this collection discuss their early lives, family, education, occupation, emigration experiences, social lives in their new homes, and any involvement in Irish American social, cultural, or fraternal organizations.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America County Societies Collection (AIA 003)
Irish Immigration Reform Movement Records (AIA 016)
Ireland House Oral History Collection (AIA 030)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Due to a lack of documentation, it is unclear when the materials were donated to the archives or by whom. The accession number associated with this gift is 1997.037.
Historical/Biographical Note
Miriam Nyhan is an Adjunct Assistant Professor of Irish Studies and Program Coordinator at New York University's Glucksman Ireland House. She received her BA and MPhil degrees from University College Cork (NUI) and her PhD from the European University Institute in Florence. Her research often focuses on oral history and Irish immigration patterns. Some of her publications include "Are You Still Below?": The Ford Marina Plant, Cork, 1917-1984, "Narration and Memory: The Experiences of the Workforce of a Ford Plant" in Irish Economic and Social History (2006), and "La Fuerza de Trabaja en Una Planta Ford" in Historia and Antropologia y Fuentes Orales (2007). She teaches courses on modern Irish history and comparative migration history.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of 21 interviews conducted by Miriam Nyhan in 2006 as part of her PhD research while studying at the European University Institute in Florence. Nyhan interviewed Irish immigrants, many of whom emigrated in the 1950s and settled in New York, to perform comparative research of Irish migration patterns. The interviewees in this collection discuss their early lives, family, education, occupation, emigration experiences, social lives in their new homes, and any involvement in Irish American social, cultural, or fraternal organizations.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Interviews are listed alphabetically by interviewee's last name.
Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Ireland -- Emigration and immigration.; Oral histories (literary works)
- Blessington, Thomas, Dec 7, 2006; cuid15095 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brady, Sean, Nov 5, 2006; cuid43787 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Brett, Martin, Oct 27, 2006; cuid15096 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Brett, Nancy, Oct 27, 2006; cuid43788 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Creegan, Mike, Oct 9, 2006; cuid43789 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cronin, Michael, Oct 11, 2006; cuid43790 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Diamond, Pat, Dec 13, 2006; cuid43791 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Fogarty, Michael and Margaret, Oct 13, 2006; cuid43792 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Jenkins, Anne, Oct 21, 2006; cuid43793 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Jennings, John, Oct 31, 2006; cuid43794 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Keane, John and Anne, Nov 14, 2006; cuid43795 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lane, Danny, Dec 13, 2006; cuid43796 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Lynch, Danny with Pat Kissane, Chris Keane and Sean Brosnan, Oct 24, 2006; cuid43797 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Lynch, Jimmy, Nov 9, 2006; cuid43798 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- McInerney, Bridie, Oct 20, 2006; cuid43799 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Morrissey, Kevin, Oct 12, 2006; cuid43800 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Murphy, Liam, May 29, 2008; cuid43801 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- O'Hanlon, Terry, Nov 1, 2005; cuid43802 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Smith, Ellen, Nov 6, 2006; cuid43803 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Thomas, Mary, Nov 10, 2006; cuid43804 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Weadock, Joe, Jun 9, 2008; cuid43805 (Box 2, Folder 10)